What if just one
lifestyle change
could help you
avoid getting cancer,
or diabetes,
or heart disease,
or high blood pressure?
This one change could cut
your risk of chronic disease
and add years to your life.
Well, the simple solution to
so many of these problems
is to eat a healthy diet.
In other words, one centered
around whole plant foods.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I'm your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
There are lots of things you can do
to reduce your risk of getting cancer.
Avoid tobacco,
maintain a healthy weight.
But one of the simplest kinds of cancer
prevention is to follow a healthy diet.
“The vast majority of cancer research
is devoted to finding cures,
rather than finding new ways
to prevent disease.”
And the results of these skewed
priorities are plain to see:
2021 is the 50th anniversary of
Nixon’s declaration of war on cancer,
and the death tolls from the
most common forms of cancer
in the United States
have continued unabated.
“We have been looking at the very
nature of cancer in the wrong way.”
Breast cancer doesn’t begin
when a lump is first detected.
All the common cancers like lung,
colorectal, breast, and prostate
(which account for the majority of deaths)
have a long latency period—
often 20 years or more.
So, it’s not like you were healthy,
and then one day you got cancer.
You haven’t been healthy—you’ve had
cancer growing in you for decades.
Indeed, there’s a bizarre
misperception that people are ‘healthy’
until they have actual
symptoms of invasive cancer.
But “[t]he barn in which hay is smoldering
before it bursts into flames
is not a safe place.”
What about using diet and nutrition
to prevent and treat cancer?
Okay, but what kind of cancer?
There are more than 200 types of cancer.
Ah, but they all share the same hallmarks.
In a series of papers cited
more than 40,000 times
in the biomedical literature, ten hallmarks
of cancer have been identified.
Increased sensitivity to growth factors;
evading your body’s tumor suppressors;
dodging your immune system;
being able to grow forever;
tumor promoting inflammation;
the ability to invade and spread
and hook up its own blood supply;
the accumulation of DNA mutations;
disarming the self-destruct
mechanisms in place;
and hijacking the cell’s metabolism.
And yes, of course, there are classes
of drugs to try to counter each one—
chemotherapy agents designed to target
each piece of the cancer puzzle.
Now ideally, there would be drugs
able to target multiple hallmarks
at the same time, but that’s
not how drugs tend to work.
And this is one of the major reasons why,
in the context of cancer research,
there are so many proponents of
investigating plant foods,
as they can deliver a cocktail of bioactive
compounds—bioactive compounds
that may target most, if not all,
of the hallmarks of cancer.
Here’s a sampling of compounds
found in fruits and vegetables
such as berries, greens, and broccoli,
shown to be able to target
each of the ten hallmarks of cancer,
at least in a petri dish.
Moreover, they ﬁt the characteristics
of an ideal chemopreventive agent.
If you were to design the perfect
candidate, you’d want them to be
selective for cancerous or
precancerous cells
while leaving normal cells alone,
be side effect free,
target most types of cancers,
be able to be consumed as a part
of a daily diet, be conveniently
available almost everywhere,
and be relatively inexpensive to boot.
And plants have all of these.
So no wonder those eating more plant-based
tend to have lower cancer rates.
However, it should be understood
that we’re not talking about
taking supplements containing extracts
or puriﬁed phytochemicals,
but rather eating whole
plant foods themselves;
more of a food-system based approach
to targeting the hallmarks of cancer.
Foods contain many thousands of
substances that lead to vast numbers
of possible interactions, yet
much of nutritional science
has long been directed towards the
impact of single dietary components.
Yes, this kind of ‘reductionist’
approach can reveal
the role of individual nutrients or
foods in the development of disease,
but let’s think about what the
optimal research strategy would be
to study the effects of bioactive
natural plant compounds
on disease prevention.
Instead of using isolated phytochemicals
in the management of cancer,
how about using whole foods, because
sometimes the whole can be
greater than the sum of its parts,
a concept known as food synergy.
Check out this study. The simultaneous
inhibition of a series
of cancer stages in breast cancer cells
using a phytochemical super-cocktail.
Two breast cancer cell lines
were treated with six different
plant compounds individually,
and then all together,
at the level you might find in
your bloodstream after eating foods
like broccoli, grapes, soybeans, and turmeric.
And while the compounds
were ineffective individually,
in combination they significantly
suppressed breast cancer
cell proliferation by
more than 80 percent,
inhibited cancer cell
migration and invasion,
stopped the cancer cells in their tracks,
and eventually killed them all off.
The plant compounds did all this
without having any deleterious effects
on the normal noncancerous
cells used as control.
No wonder the foundation of cancer
prevention, based on an update
of the most extensive report on
diet and cancer ever published
is not pills, but plants.
Cut down on alcohol, soda,
meat, and processed junk,
and center your diet around whole grains,
vegetables, fruits, and beans.
In our next story, we look
at whether choosing organic
over conventional fruits and vegetables
could protect against cancer.
In a review updating the evidence
on human exposure and toxicity
of pesticides, the body of evidence
linking pesticide exposure
and cancer is said to be so
huge that the role of pesticides
in cancer development
can no longer be doubted.
But most of the evidence that shows
DNA damage from pesticides is from
occupational exposure among
farmers and workers in the fields,
the pesticide industry itself, or
those living in high spray areas.
There is evidence linking
non-occupational exposure
to pesticides to DNA damage —
in this case single- and
double-stranded DNA
fragmentation in sperm of men —
with higher levels of pesticides
flowing through their bodies —
but that was in China, where the
average pesticide concentrations
are as much as four times higher
than in some other parts of the world.
Another way pesticides could
potentially facilitate tumor growth
is through adverse effects
on anticancer immunity.
NK cells, natural killer cells,
are our body's first line
of white blood cell defense against
cancer cells and virus-infected cells.
And pesticides have been shown
to induce harmful effects
on these defender cells, reducing
their ability to kill off tumor cells.
For example, if you put a bunch
of natural killer cells in a petri dish
along with human leukemia cells
without any pesticide, your natural
killer cells can clean house and wipe
out more than half of the cancer.
But if you drip a tiny bit of pesticide
on, your NK cells are so disabled
that the cancer wins the day.
Okay, but how much
pesticide are we talking?
The researchers used the
maximum level found in those
actively spraying pesticides.
Most of us, however,
are privileged enough not
to be forced into such a job.
So what about looking at just
the residual pesticides left
on conventional produce?
Is choosing organic for cancer
prevention worth the investment?
In the United States, more than 90%
of the population has detectable
pesticides in their urine and blood,
regardless of where they work or live.
And we know it's from the food
we eat because crossover trials —
where people are switched between
consuming conventionally grown
and organic foods — show you can
turn on and off urinary concentrations
of pesticide metabolites
like a light switch.
But that doesn't necessarily mean
the pesticides are harming you.
The health consequences
of consuming pesticide residues
from conventionally grown
foods remain unknown.
But a recent study did find
that those who self-reported
the highest frequency
of organic food consumption
had about a 25% lower
risk of getting cancer.
And here it is: the first of its kind
to evaluate the association
between frequency of organic food
consumption and cancer risk,
controlling for a wide
array of other factors.
Doesn't it matter that organic
consumers are younger?
The researchers controlled
for that and still found
significantly lower cancer risk.
Okay, but maybe organic consumers
get less cancer because
they're more affluent, or
more highly educated,
or skinnier or exercise more,
or eat less meat, or smoke less.
Nope, they controlled for all that
and still found significantly lower
cancer risk in organic consumers.
Maybe their diets were different
in other ways though:
more fruits and vegetables
overall or less junk food?
Nope, they still found
significantly lower cancer risk.
They concluded: our results indicate
that higher organic food consumption
is indeed associated with a reduction
in the risk of overall cancer.
This is the most sophisticated study
of its type to date, but there was
an earlier study that was even bigger,
and little evidence was found
for a decrease in the
incidence of all cancers
except for perhaps one kind of
blood cancer, non-Hodgkin lymphoma.
Here are the data.
No difference in cancer overall
between those who never choose
organic or those who usually or always
do, with the only significant findings:
a lower risk of non-Hodgkin lymphoma
and an increased risk of breast cancer.
Is it possible that women who choose
organic food are more conscientious
about getting screened
for breast cancer and that
explains the higher diagnosis rate?
We really don't know.
Of course, what we care about
the most is not just cancer
but so-called all-cause mortality,
the risk of dying prematurely, period,
and higher blood levels of a pesticide
known as beta-hexachlorocyclohexane
are associated with living
a significantly shorter life.
How do we cut down on our levels?
Well, there was a study done way back
when that found that the breast milk
of a vegetarian mother was found to
have less beta-hexachlorocyclohexane
than the milk of her sister, who
was also breast-feeding at the time,
but included meat in her diet.
The vegetarian sister apparently
had levels of that pesticide
that were lower by about a third,
compared with her omnivorous sibling.
No surprise, since this class of
chlorinated pesticides are fat soluble,
so they're found most frequently
in foods of animal origin.
A more recent study failed to look
at beta-hexachlorocyclohexane,
but they did find that chlorinated
PCBs were associated
with increased mortality risk.
And again, the toxins were found
in the same kinds of foods:
dairy products, eggs,
and animal fats.
So, no surprise, the blood of those
eating vegan was found to be
significantly less polluted
than omnivores
regarding a whole series
of PCBs, including those found
in the study to be associated
with increased mortality,
but the vegans did not have lower
levels of beta-hexachlorocyclohexane.
The bottom line is that if you're
worried about the adverse
health effects of pesticides
and pesticide-type compounds,
you may want to lower
your intake of animal products.
But when it comes to fruits
and vegetables, the benefits
of consuming conventionally
grown produce are likely
to outweigh any possible risks
from pesticide exposure.
So concerns over pesticide risks
should not discourage us
from stuffing our faces with as many
fruits and vegetables as possible.
That would give us
a huge health benefit,
whereas the potential lifelong
damage of any pesticides
on those same fruits and
veggies has been estimated
to only cut a few minutes
off a person's life, on average,
which is nothing compared
to the nutritional benefits
of eating more fruits and vegetables.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts Podcast
landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite to each of these topics.
My latest two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”,
available on e-book, audiobook,
or actual book.
And the “How Not to Diet Cookbook”,
with more than 100 recipes for
delicious and nutritious meals.
All the proceeds I receive from
the sales of my books go to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the website is free.
There’s no ads, no corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.